Poul Anderson

The Serpent in Eden

Regardless, the planet was beautiful.

Even as the aircraft bucked and shuddered, caught in the hurricane shriek, Janne Granstad remembered Cleopatra seen from, space. Against night and stars the globe had glowed, blue with its oceans, green, gold, and umber with its lands, swirled silvery with its clouds. The brighter light of the whiter sun made those hues at once more vivid and more serene than Earth’s, whose loveliness had always lured tears out upon her lashes. And then the diamond sweep of the ring!

Outside the windows, blackness and lightning raved. Violence toned through metal and bones. The craft lurched insanely, threw her against her seat .harness till straps dug into flesh. Arch Fielding turned his head around from the controls. She could just make out his cry: “No use. We haven’t got the ceiling to get above this stuff. I’ll have to ride it out till—” Janne lost the rest of his words.

She thought, dimly astonished: That shouldn’t be. Should it? Nd storm should be that tall. But, of course, we aren’t on Earth, Earth is nearly 400 light-years south of here. . . . No, wait, “south” doesn’t mean the same any longer, Cleopatra doesn’t have the same lodestar. . . .

Roberto de Banos leaned across the narrow aisle between their seats to take her hand. That was almost more bewildering. Or was it? He gave her a stiff smile and said amidst the fury, “Don’t be afraid. This is a stout vessel. While we stay aloft, we are safe.”

Are we? Janne asked in dread. At once: No, I must not panic. We have too many unknowns around us to conjure up needless ones. The laws of nature are the same here as they are at home, or in the farthest galaxy. Only the parameters are changed. And not very much. We can live here. We can walk unarmored beneath a sky and breathe an air men have never befouled, we can wash our bodies inside and out with the purity of waters, we can taste the fruits of an untainted soil. Earth today may be more alien to man than is Cleopatra.

But don’t think despair of any kind. Think prose, think science. Her mind almost chanted: The F7 sun gives us a third again the terrestrial irradiation, a higher proportion of it in energetic particles and quanta. The lower gravity, 0.86, means air pressure dropping more slowly with altitude. The rotation period is less too, seventeen and a third hours, making stronger Coriolis force. The smaller size of the planet may be a factor, bringing climatic zones closer together. And how many more variables have we overlooked? No wonder storms are big, wild, and so unforeseeable by us that this one actually caught us in flight.

There was courage in the dry recital. But the weather ramped on, and on, and on, driving the aircraft helpless before it.

And when at last clouds broke, sunlight speared through, wind faded as swiftly as it had arisen, Fielding told his companions in a stark voice: “We’ve gone on too long. Fuel’s about finished. I’ll have to set us down on the first decent-looking ground I spot.”

Peering through the pane beside her, Janne made out crags tumbling toward endless forests. But on the horizon, the sun low above, glimmered what had to be ocean. Then they’d crossed this whole small subtropical continent, caught in the westward half of the cyclone. Base Island lay 2000 kilometers behind. The magnitude of thit struck her like a blow.

De Barros said, “Don’t be reckless, Fielding. Husband your reserves. Don’t descend unless we are all three positive it is safe.”

“Shut up,” the pilot snapped. “I’ll be the judge of that.”

De Barros grew rigid. “I think you are exhausted and overwrought,” he said. “Granted, you are the most experienced flyer, but not at present the best. Let me take over.”

“Not” Fielding yelled, and threw a curse after it.

“Or Dr. Granstad might,” de Barros suggested, as if she were not on first-name terms with both men.

Jarme shrank back in her seat. “Don’t,” she whispered. ‘Please. I—I’m sure Arch can—”

“I was thinking mainly of your welfare,” de Barros told her, but had the wit to pursue the argument no further.

Janne took refuge in watching Caesar sink, red and gold, toward the sea without a name. How small the sun was. Or—wait—it was farther away than Sol is from Earth. Otherwise Cleopatra would have been scorched barren. By day one didn’t notice the size of the disk—who could look near it?—but when coastal haze gentled its brilliance, the horizon illusion exaggerated the difference

“Hang on,” Fielding said over his shoulder. “Pray if you want. And if we don’t make it ... Janne, I’m glad to have known you.”

He gave himself back to his flying. The craft slanted downward. A wide sandy beach appeared in the forward panes, grew with terrifying speed, leaped and struck.

The vehicle bounced. Teeth rattled in jaws. Across hundreds of meters, their dunes and tricky little airs, Fielding brought his machine to a halt.

When peace had thundered upon them, Janne would have flung off her harness and kissed him. But he twisted his neck to confront de Barros and said nastily, “That’s how come I didn’t want you at the console.”

De Barros shocked her himself when he replied, cool-voiced, “My compliments on your good luck, at least. Does it extend to establishing communication with Base?”

They knew it did not.

Night was reined sorcery.

The strand glimmered white, the wilderness behind lifted cupolas of darkness against stars and remote snow-peaks, the ocean before played a.million sparkles, light-ripples, glades, and the huge broken ring-image across its ebony. Waves rolled hush-hush-hush, the ever gentle surf of Cleopatra. Breezes were mild, bearing alike the smells of salt reaches and green growth. Sand was still warm underfoot, fine enough to yield like flesh caressed. Somewhere, something unknown trilled a song.

Stars glistened in the middle heaven as if to crowd out a black which itself felt luminous. Meteors went among them, streak after silent streak. Northward they were lost in leaping banners of aurora, white, blue, violet, ice green, and ghostly rose. Southward soared the ring. The dust, gravel, and stones which had once been a moon had become a wan rainbow that reached a third of the way up the sky, along which trafficked hasty, flashing, and tumbling jewels in their hundreds. At this season, early winter, the shadow of the planet did not quite scoop out the middle of the arch; the ogive it made was almost visibly rising as night moved onward.

And then lifted Charmian, the larger of the two fragments which men had found worthy of a name. Was the name worthy of her? However tiny, at her nearness she showed as big as Luna seen from Earth. She was less bright—hardly even a globe, rough, scarred, changeable as she spun, though often a scoured spot of metal caught a sunbeam and flared—but she did not have to shine through city fumes and glare; she kindled the waters.

At their edge, Janne roused from her watching to think, guiltily, that she ought not to have wandered from the men. She could see them, distance-dwindled, as they began setting up camp. The glow-stove became an abrupt crimson star. She noticed she was hungry. Why didn’t they call me to come do my share? I drifted away because it seemed they’d be fiddling with the radio and squabbling with each other for hours yet. In pain: Why must they, here in a miracle?

She started back, a tall and limber young woman, yellow hair chopped off below the ears and coverall ,..arelessly worn, but her body possessing the handsomeness of good structure well tended. Being at the core a practical person, as is the duty of any explorer, she answered herself: Well, it’s not a miracle without its troubles and dangers. They’re under strain, Arch and Roberto. We could die. That doesn’t seem likely, in this moment’s majesty; but what will we find tomorrow, or what will find us?

She knew there was no foretelling. A planet is a world, infinite in the number of its faces and mysteries. The fifty people who Hanno had brought were the first who ever saw Cleopatra. Before them, nothing except a robot vessel had made that enormous journey and returned to report its discoveries. They amounted to little more than the fact of an orb which seemed to be habitable and uninhabited. Machines can only find what ignorant men have programmed them to find.

And, in the weeks since arrival, the expedition had barely begun to learn. The data which observers aboard the orbiting ship could gather were valuable but lean. Those who went down and established themselves on Base Island had studied it, and the mainland shore opposite, with fanatic intensity; but they had necessarily concentrated on things like the chemistry of rocks and life, rather than topography or natural history. This flight was among the first intended to go farther inland. It was supposed to fare some few hundred kilometers, descending here and there for a closer look, returning within three or four days. Instead ...

Janne shrugged. Wryness twitched her mouth upward. We named you better than we knew, Cleopatra. Lovely but—hm—capricious.

Fielding, who had been hunkered over food preparation, rose as she approached. Though everyone was now too used to the lesser weight to notice it, he, who had been a trifle awkward at home, was graceful here. He was a lanky man with a bush of black hair and features she thought were good-looking in their broad-nosed deep-brown fashion. They had found much in common on the long voyage hither, after they saw it was best to set political differences aside. He remembered with pleasure a visit to her Norway; it was less ruined than most of Earth, he said. She had studied in his North America. Their professions did not really sunder them either, he an engineer, she a naturalist; nobody on this trip could afford to be narrowly specialized.

“Hi,” he said. “Want to take over cooking? Short rations need a woman’s touch.”

“Short?” she asked.

Fielding jerked his head at de Banos, who was raising the tent. “He insists. Says we may be stranded for quite a spell.”

The Brazilian left his own work to come and say, “It is an obvious possibility.” As always, his slender form was neatly outfitted and soldierly erect. Upon the thin-sculptured head, prematurely gray hair and mustache had gone argent in this light. His English was less fluent that the others’, but he spoke it when with them, rather than the official Portuguese or Japanese of the expedition. Janne didn’t know whether that was a gesture of friendship or of condescension. Perhaps it was one toward her, another toward Fielding. In spite of the North American’s radicalism, she felt she understood him; both their countries remembered not only having once been prosperous and democratic, but hay‘ ing once been satellites of nobody else. Aristocrats, however, were outside her experience, whether baronial Brazilians or magnates of the New Empire.

“You mean,” she asked, half timidly, “the radio interference will keep on for long?”

“I am not positive,” de Banos admitted. “Our knowledge of stars like Caesar is less than complete. Still,, storms upon them have been seen to remain at peak for as much as two terrestrial weeks. Until the present one diminishes, no transmission of ours will carry all the way we have come from Base.”

His redundant last sentence made Fielding scowl at ‘what could be a subtle insult. But as if to emphasize, the auroras suddenly flamed high and lurid. The shadows they cast danced across the beach. Janne gasped in awe.

“We are too small to be located from space, and only two of the aircraft have ample range to get here and back, if our whereabouts are known beforehand,” de Barros continued, likewise unnecessarily. “Hence we must wait till we can send a message and, I suppose, have fuel brought us. It seems common sense to stretch out our food supplies.”

Fielding’s hand chopped at the forest. “When we’ve got a whole continent and ocean full of eatables?” he scoffed.

“Are you sure it is?” Janne cautioned.

“Why shouldn’t it be? Life uses the same basic stuff everywhere else on a planet. And conditions on this coast don’t seem especially different from the east.”

“You’re assuming a great deal, Arch.”

For an instant Janne feared that Fielding would gibe at de Barros with something unspeakably obvious of his own. Perhaps: “Yes, I understand that while similar environments have produced basically similar biochem—istries on two planets, the parallelisms couldn’t be exact. Cleopatran flesh and fruit lack some of the compounds we must have, like certain vitamins; and a proportion is turning out to be poisonous to us. This has its advantages. It works both ways. Cleopatran diseases can’t get a foothold in us. And we can supplement our diets, deliciously, if we’re careful.”

But instead the North American gave her one of his full-lipped smiles and said, “Right. I know what close relatives the potato, the tomato, and the deadly nightshade are. Don’t worry. I won’t eat anything you haven’t certified as a type we checked out on Base and proved was safe. I am betting we’ll find a lot hereabouts.

Though such identifications were part of Jane’s job; she felt unhappy at the responsibility. Seeking words to explain, she turned her gaze outward, along the shining, beach. What she saw made her go taut.

De Barros noticed. “O que hd?” he exclaimed. “Shhhh.” She pointed.

A hundred meters away, a creature had stepped from the forest onto the sand. Light shimmered off a tall, thin, eerily manlike body. It halted, crouched bent-legged, and peered at the strangers.

She heard a slither as Fielding drew his gun. “Don’t shoot,” she whispered frantically.

“I’m playing it cautious, no more,” he assured her. “Damn, isn’t that something!”

All personnel went armed. Thus far there had been no need for it, except to collect specimens. Janne had been glad of that; and, necessary and fascinating though dissections were, she hated seeing slain animals brought to her laboratory shack. It reminded her too sharply of whale and elephant, stag and lion, every kind of wildlife much bigger than a rat or a roach, which Earth knew only in archives. Yonder one, erect, alert, brought back to her some chimpanzees she had once seen in a film 0 God, almost human faces, faunlike awareness behind the eyes. . . .

Frozen, the forest dweller watched them.

De Barros was first to move, charily, back to a pile of gear. Janne glimpsed him draw forth a pair of night glasses and bring them to focus.

She had never before seen him shaken.

“Madre scatter burst from him. He dropped the, binoculars. She snatched them up for herself. The Animal sprang into clear view.

Startled by the noise and movement, it was loping’ back to cover. In its left hand—not paw, hand—it: gripped a rock shaped and edged by what must be chipping.

It vanished. Charmian, entering the shadow of the. planet, turned dull coppery-red.

At dawn Janne again strayed off by herself and stood looking over the sea. It had awakened to a million blues and greens, white-laced where waves met land. Out upon some reefs basked scores of great long-necked marine reptiloids. Their numbers bespoke how rich in life these waters must be. The sky, cloudless, was already too lightful for the ring to show, except for a swift phantomlike has, Charmian’s half-sized companion. But it was not empty, that sky. Thousands of wings shared it with the sun. Clamor drifted down to meet the low surf noise.

Shadows were long, more blue and sharp than on Earth. The air was brisk, barely on the cool side of balmy, laden with fragrances which mostly were different from those of sunset or night.

“Good morning,” said de Barros,

Janne turned to greet him. Immaculate, he offered his usual slight bow. “Did you sleep well, since you have risen this early?” he inquired.

“No, I was too excited,” she said. “But I don’t mind.” Impulsively: “I can’t get over the—the abundance here. The whole horizon seems bigger.” It wasn’t in fact, she knew. The equatorial diameter of Cleopatra was 9920 kilometers, 78 percent of Earth’s, which meant that, under present conditions, she could see about one kilometer less far.

He surprised her by saying, “It is.” After a moment: “This marvelously clear atmosphere. Vision isn’t caged by pollution. Perhaps I could show you something comparable on our estate in Rio Grande do Sul, the grasslands.. . . But no.” He shook his head. “They are an enclave which will last no longer than our family’s wealth and power. Meanwhile, every wind brings filth.” He sighed. “Here on Cleopatra—Janne, I begin to understand why my ancestors worshipped the Virgin.”

What? she thought. Is the aristocrat baring his soul? And then: No. I shouldn’t be sarcastic when he’s trying to be friendly.

It wasn’t the first time, either, she recalled. De Barros had found occasion after occasion to talk to her. That wasn’t easy. Besides his being a planetologist, a scholar of rocks, magmas, inanimate forces, there was the, lack of privacy on Base Island. No two people were ever far from others; it might not be safe. And, well, Arch has been particularly likely to interrupt.

“You’ve seen several new planets,” she said, for lack of better words.

“None like this,” de Barros answered. “They had their wonders, but men could never make a home on them. A world where we can live, truly live, is more rare and precious than we can well imagine. It is like being given-Eden back, to try again.”

“Do you think people might colonize here?” It had often been speculated about, but the general feeling was that Caesar was too remote from Sol, at the end of too long a haul. It would never be possible to ship very many emigrants; and they would be more isolated than ever were Pilgrim Fathers—or Greenland Norse, who died. out.

“Oh yes, indeed. Let them see our account, and those who can will sell whatever they possess to buy a one-way passage and barely enough equipment for a start.”

“But ... cut off ... and the uncertainties, the dangers ...”

“Janne, I can name you a good many persons who would not mind in the least being cut off from our present excuse for a civilization. I rather suspect I am among, them. As for danger, in a very few more generations Cleopatra at her ‘worst will be safer than Earth at her best.”

“You can’t think that: you!” she blurted.

De Barros shrugged. “I am a scientist, who abhors politics and the military. But coming from the family I do, I cannot avoid noticing things, including things the public is not to be told. We are far closer to a far more serious ecological crisis, and the international balance of power is far more precarious, than the insiders admit even to themselves.”

Janne winced. “How I hope you are wrong.”

He cocked his head. “Forgive me. I,didn’t mean to distress you on such a gorgeous morning. Let us therefore simply speak of adventure, opportunity, freedom, healthful and beautiful surroundings. Consider yourself. You stand so raptly watching those animals. There must be work for a hundred lifetimes of naturalists. Would you not be happier here than anyplace else?”

Janne bit her lip.

“Why are you sad all at once?” he asked low, and took her ann.

“That being,” she got out through a thickness in her gullet.

“Ah. The tool-bearer.”

“Yes. I did daydream about pioneering, when it didn’t seem Cleopatra had intelligent life. But now .. .”

“Marvelous in truth. To be sure, what we saw appeared less developed than man.”

janne shook her head. “I got a pretty good look at the hand ax. It’s made as well as specimens from Earth’s Paleolithic were . . . by Homo sapiens. Oh, perhaps you can’t teach calculus to the maker. But perhaps you can. And even if not, his breed must be on their way, well on their way, to becoming as bright as we are—their own kind of consciousness, which surely can’t be the same as ours.”

“You wish to learn more about them, do you not?”

“ Wish’ is a feeble word. I was afire until—Roberto, are you certain colonists will be coming?”

“Yes, if we don’t discover some terrible obstacle.”

“Maybe we can.”

He considered her before saying, “You are afraid that man, permanently on Cleopatra, would destroy the aborigines.”

“I am. Think what he did to his fellow men who were wea.ker, or to the dolphins and apes. I could hope he’d have the sense to learn from Earth and use a new planet right. But don’t you see, whatever he did, he’d be using it. Making it his, changing it, dominating.... He might grant natives a few wretched reservations. No more. What then of their own dreams, everything they might have done, might have given to the universe? No,” Janne said through tears, “I don’t want to be a party to that. How could I ever dare die?”

She fought for calmness. De Barros ventured to lay a hand on her shoulder. “Easy, easy,” he murmured, “You are borrowing trouble. Let us first learn the facts—whatever we can—seeing that we must be here for awhile anyway. You have never had a more fascinating challenge, have you?”

“No,” she confessed, and felt a surprised gratitude that he should be this understanding. He’s really a good person, she thought.

“Uh-hum!” said Fielding at their backs. “For your information, I’ve found where the nearest fresh water is. So how about you making breakfast?”

The men matched fingers to decide who should accompany Janne on her first excursion, and who guard camp. Fielding won; at any rate, he seemed to regard it as a victory. De Barros philosophically said he could study a nearby outcrop. Cleopatran petrology had its duplications of the terrestrial, but already at Base he had discovered differences which a geologist would call spectacular.

The other two collected their equipment. While not planning to go far, they carried compasses—the planet had a stronger magnetic field than Earth—and small transceivers—the electrical chaos in the upper atmosphere wouldn’t stop short-range radio, if one didn’t mind static. In addition, they bore weapons, first-aid kits, Jarme’s professional tools, and a couple of sand—wiches.

Travel was simple—no tangled brush to fight. Cleoliatran plants did not seem to have evolved as far as angiosperms, at least on this continent. However elabo—

tre gestive of ferns, lycopods, fungus, or evergreen trees, most were wildly exotic. Besides every possible shade of verdure, the forest had its bursts of vivid red, purple, yellow—not true flowers, but poinsettia-like pseudo blooms.

It was warm and quiet here, a checkerboard of bright openness and sun-speckled shadow, a multitude of odors sweet, pungent, pleasantly rank. Most of the abundant animals were small and not noisy. Insectoids buzzed or hummed. A swarm of smidgins passed, the tiny individuals merged into a cloud; two leathery-winged reptiloids flapped along, leisurely feasting. A jackadandy flaunted plumes of a sort, though it wasn’t a bird either, and trilled. The largest beasts seen were half a dozen hipposaur, grazing at a distance. But Janne was utterly charmed when she came upon a reptiloid new to her, likewise a peaceful herbivore. It could afford pacifism,, being a two-meter-wide walking dome of bony armor and spiky tail. “We must call that a hoplite!” she said clapping her hands together.

“Huh?” Fielding asked. “It doesn’t look as if it could even hop heavy.”

Janne laughed. “An infantryman in classical Greece.  Roberto was telling me, several days ago ...”

“Oh. I’m afraid my education’s been neglected. Come on; if you want to search for natives, we should keep moving.

His sourness drew a troubled regard from her. “What’s the matter, Arch?”

“Ah, hungry, I guess. That stupid rationing ... No, that isn’t really it. I think you can see what it is.”

Her cheeks heated. She decided r(ot to reply. They walked on for a number of minutes.

“Okay, damn it. I’ll speak out,” Fielding said. “It’s that Brazilian bastard, and you getting chummy with him.”

“I know you’d overthrow his class, his entire country—and you know I don’t agree that violent revolution ever improved anything—but, Arch,” Janne pleaded, “we’re human beings together, a long, long way from home.”

“He hasn’t left his interests behind. You can bet your blood he’s figuring how his relatives can get a stranglehold on this planet—squeeze out the Japanese, sure, but.make peons out of the settlers—”

“He isn’t! We’ve talked—”

“Yeah, he wants you in his bag also. Janne, you may be a little naive, but you’re not stupid. You know the signs.”

I do, sighed within her. Inescapable, perhaps. We aren’t many women along; and /—her fingers knotted together—I’m one of the few who are neither solidly attached to a man nor, available to a lot of them.... The psychologists should have picked the crew more carefully. Did they try and fail? It must be hard to find qualified volunteers among Earth’s poverty-trapped masses.

Fielding stared before him as he tramped and added harshly, “I suppose you’ve seen them on me too.”

“You—you’re sweet,” she stammered, “but—”

“But not just what you’re after? Who is, then? A rich Brazilian? I’m not sweet at all. I can be as mean as necessary to keep him from getting you.”

Janne bridled. “Arch, you’re overstepping.”

“No. I’m worried sick. You don’t understand how rotten his type is. Why, I’d rather see you the mistress of Captain Yoshida than the wife—the toy, the slave—of—”

“Nok! Enough! You’re making me understand why Roberto loathes fanatics. Stop slandering him before I stop liking you.”

He swallowed. They continued, through a land where she could no longer find beauty.

But after more minutes a new sound broke the silence between them. They halted, strained their ears, stared at each other with anger forgotten. Janne’s heart leaped. She beckoned Fielding to follow her, well behind; she could move more quietly than he.

A screen of something like tall bracken rose in front of the clattering. Janne crept up to it, parted stalks and fronds, peered through.

What I thought! What I both hoped and feared it would be.

The creature squatted in a glade where a ridge of flinty rock thrust above soil. It was a reptiloid, hairless; small scales were darkly iridescent in the sunlight. Erect on clawed feet, it would overtop her by a few centimeters. The frame, unobscured by clothes or ornaments, was manlike in a sense. Its alienness—lean barrel of a torso, long, curiously jointed legs, short arms and the way they hung from the shoulder, slender tail—did not make it grotesque; this body had its own grace, its own integrity. The neck was likewise long, flexible, supporting a narrow head. The eyes were its best feature, large and golden, protected by arching ridges that, with the membranous crest on top, made the skull resemble an ancient helmet. The face was flat, a single nostril slit in place of a nose, mouth V-shaped in a perpetual grin, jaws of nearly human delicacy.

When they opened, the variety of teeth indicated that here too was an omnivore.

Here too were hands. They were not hominid. Instead of a thumb, four claw-tipped fingers radiated in a half-circle from the palm. But they worked as welL The Cleopatran was making a coup-de-poing.

Janne had studied a little prehistory. She recognized the technique. A bone held in one hand struck pieces off a chunk of—rock which the other gripped. The labor went fast, in clash and sparks. The resulting outline would be a thin spear, pointed, sharp-rimmed, about twenty centimeters in length. It would be an all-purpose weapon and tool; the user could throw it to knock down small game, or cut, crush, flense, butcher, scrape, slice, carve. When it grew dull, a new edge was easily put on; when it broke or was lost, a replacement was quickly made. Shards heaped on the pseudomoss showed that generations had used this site.

Hand axes, scarcely to be told from the one taking shape, had been found throughout Earth’s eastern half by the many thousands—man’s main reliance through tens of millennia.

Man: the tool-bearing animal. Then how can we deny the spirit yonder?

The Cleopatran raised its head and stared. Its tail switched. Fielding joined Janne, his gun held steady. A single explosive bullet could blow the stoneworker in two.

“Don’t shoot,” she breathed.

“If it acts threatening, I will,” he answered. “You’re worth more than any glorified snake.”

The Cleopatran rose, hefting the almost finished ax and the bone shaper. Despite herself, Janne tensed to duck. However, the being merely regarded them. A breeze brought its musky odor.

She held out her open hands. “Vi er venner,” she said. At once the humor of stating “We are friends”—in Norwegiant—kicked a giggle from her, half hysterical.

“He can’t know we’re not some funny kind of beast,” Fielding muttered. “In fact, we are.”

“Until we communicate,” Janne replied. The thought flitted: Yes, let’s say “he.” Cleopatran life has two sexes like ours. I’m not sure which this person is, but “it” isn’t right. She stooped, with an idea of scratching patterns in the ground. The being retreated, vanished in brake and shadows.

“Cautious,” Fielding opined. “After all, we’re two to one. Maybe he figured you were about to throw a finder at him. Or maybe he’s gone after his buddies. I think we’d better head straight for camp.”

Reluctant and disappointed, Janne nonetheless had to agree. She rose and they began walking. “I don’t expect they’ll be hostile,” she argued. “Why should they? The lower animals don’t fear us; they’ve never learned to. ... Still, I could imagine—well, being trampled by a horde of eager curiosity-seekers.”

“Or whatever. I’d feel more trustful if they were mammals.”

“Theroids,” Janne corrected automatically. “There don’t seem to be any true mammals around, just primitive little animals that don’t even lactate.”

“A cold-blooded, egg-laying thinker. . . . It feels wrong.” The engineer grimaced.

“Why? Remember, the reptiloids of Cleopatra—many of them—are further evolved than reptiles on Earth. They have efficient hearts, for instance. I suppose the planet’s being warmer, probably never having had an ice age, gives less relative advantage to homeothermic over poikilothermic organisms, so the latter have had more chance to develop onward.”

“Homeo—huh?” Fielding scowled. “Never mind. I admit to being prejudiced in favor of mammals. You, no doubt, consider this the most wonderful thing we could have found.”

“Of course.” Janne hesitated. “Or the most dreadful.”

“How that? You don’t imagine men have much to fear from a bunch of savages, do you?”

“Yes. They have to fear what they’ll be tempted to do.” Janne told him her forebodings.

His air of distaste turned to one of reined-in-fury. “And de Barros encouraged you in that sentimentalism? I guess I shouldn’t be surprised. It’d make a nice additional excuse—protecting natives—for aristos to keep their feet on settlers.”

“What do you mean, Arch?” she exclaimed. “That men should come and ... take their world away from these people ... destroy them?”

“If need be. When you’ve seen, lived with, slum children whose faces were gnawed by rats—and I have you won’t let a bunch of scaly, lipless things stand between them and a chance at a decent existence.” After a moment: “Oh, I don’t advocate extermination, unless we must. We can maintain preserves.”

It scarcely eased the horror in her. She had nothing to say while they returned.

Their route was different from before. Near the coast Fielding halted. A stand of dactylophytes, looking like fleshy shrubs, glowed golden-green. “Hey!” he said. Porkplant.”

Janne roused from her mood to answer, “Or a close relative.”

“Well, for heavens sake, let’s collect a bundle and come back after more. Now our bellies won’t growl.” Analysis and experiment on Base Island had shown that the fronds were tasty as well as nutritious to man—not a complete diet, of course, but a welcome supplement.

“I don’t know,” Janne said. “We haven’t a biochemical laboratory along.”

“Why should we need any, for this? Sure, first you put a sample under your microscope and check if it’s the exact same species, free of parasites or whatever. I’ll bet you a month’s pay you’ll report positive.”

“I wish you wouldn’t eat it, Arch.”

She failed to dissuade him. In camp, she found he was right about the classification. Nonetheless, she re—

fused a share. De Barros smiled wryly and said, “You may guess whether or not I am disguising cowardice when I declare that if a lady is to go hungry, so will I.”

Fielding, his pleasure dashed, glowered at them and grumbled, “Well, at least one of us will keep his strength up.” At dinner he feasted ostentatiously.

Next morning a Cleopatran appeared on the beach. It wasn’t the same as yesterday’s, being of lesser size and having only a rudimentary crest. Janne guessed it was a female, while her previous encounter had been with a male. The creature carried a hand ax of her own. She poised a distance from the aircraft and, when Janne drew slowly near, hissed and made as if to cast the weapon. Janne halted. They exchanged stares for a minute, until the girl tossed a gift of porkplant. The Cleopatran took it up, ate it, and sidled back into the forest.

To de Barros, who had guarded her, Janne remarked, “They really are shy, aren’t they? I suppose they think we’re supernatural.”

“Let us do the traditional thing,” the Bruilian suggested: “set forth some trinkets for the next visitor.”

Having brought none, they improvised, deciding what could be sacrificed in the way of bright cloth, buttons, a hand mirror, a diffraction grating. It was fun. Janne wondered if they might not be a touch light-headed from hunger, they laughed so much. No, she concluded; it was de Barros’ considerable stock of dry humor. The pangs weren’t bad, just a continuous reminder that she had a stomach. Tight rationing was not the same as starvation.

It struck them that colored polaroid photographs should make ideal gifts, and they went about looking for good subjects. Fielding found them at that.

In well-fed vigor, he had gone off to try his luck fishing. (The proper word, “ichthyoiding,” was unlikely ever to become popular.) His catch had been abundant; one needed merely drop a hook or sweep a net through these swarming waters. When he saw Janne and de Barros side by side, composing a picture of pseudo-blooms, he flung his creel at her feet. “There you are,” he snapped.

“What do you mean, Arch?” she asked uncertainly.

His gaze smoldered. “I wanted as many different new species as I could snag for you,” he said. Seems like you’d rather hang around camp playing games.”—

“That isn’t fair,” de Barros protested. “We are trying to establish communication with the natives.” , “Yah, yah, yah.” Fielding stalked from them.

Janne spoke in pain: “That isn’t like him.”

“He does not care for me,” said de Barros.

“But he’s never been this ... childish.”

“Let him sulk.”

The enjoyment was gone from her undertaking. She and the planetologist finished it, though, laying forth their offerings at the spot where the Cleopatran had twice emerged (if it was the same they had spied the night before last). Thereafter they waited. Fielding ate a big lunch, and later sought his sleeping bag for a nap. That wasn’t characteristic either.

The return of the being drove concern about him from Janne’s mind. The slender, sheening form trod daintily from behind the dactylophytes. Grown less wary of aircraft, tent, and humans, she stopped, peered their way, and neither retreated nor threatened when Janne advanced. “Hasn’t she seen our presents?” the girl wondered aloud. She tossed a chunk of porkplant in among them. The Cleopatran promptly went after it, picked it up, and stuffed it in her mouth. When no more was forthcoming, she wandered on down the beach. Bewildered, Janne and de Barros stared after her.

Abruptly she must have noticed signs, for she squatted. Sand flew beneath her scooping hand ax. .Soon she reached into the hole she had made and drew forth some equivalent of a clam. With the tool she pried it open and severed meat from the shell. Having eaten, she returned inland.

Man and woman did not speak for a long time.

“I’ve got to learn more,” Janne said, over and over, that evening. “Track our visitor down to her community or ... or whatever we find. It’ll be safe, I’m sure. They’ve been gentle, even timid. But don’t you see, this is an impossible paradox, toolmakers who ignore new artifacts. If we don’t come to understanding it, who knows what surprises may be sprung on us—back at Base too? Besides, as short of manpower as the whole expedition is, we have a duty to use what time we’re bound to spend here.”

De Barros opposed her going herself. In the end he yielded, on condition he accompany her. She was much the best suited for such an investigation. He adapted a portable gas detector. Given a fresh scent—the natives left a strong one—and duly adjusted, its meter’s needle was as good a tracker as the bloodhounds of history.

Fielding had said little, except to complain that he felt poorly. During the night his illness rocketed.

A sound of vomiting roused Janne. She hastened from her bag and out of the„ tent. Under the stars, meteors, ring, and aurora, Fielding crouched on the sand. He heaved and shuddered. When she laid arms around him, she felt sweat upon icy skin.

“Roberto!” she wailed. “Wake up, help, help!”

Between them, they got the North American cleansed and brought back into shelter. By the light of their flashbeams, his eyeballs rolled white. Lips pulled parched away from teeth. “Here,” de Barros said, “here is a cup of water.”

“Not from you,” Fielding mumbled. “You poisoned me. Or she did. Lied to me . . . so I wou’n’ connerdic’ whatever lie she’ll tell ‘bout this planet to save her damn snakes. . . . Murderers, both o’ you—”

Dawn walked russet over the mountains. Waves glittered and whooshed beneath a salt breeze. Winged life went aloft in its thousands.

Outside the tent, where Fielding lay in feverish sleep, Janne and de Banos traded looks. “You didn’t believe what he accused me of, did you?” the man rasped.

“Of course not.” She shook his hands.

“I am not . . . ruthless. Neither are my kinfolk. He sees us as tyrants and schemers. He cannot see troubled people trying their clumsy human best to cope with a worsening world.”

9 can, Roberto. I don’t think your way of coping is alirays right, but your good will I’ve never doubted—nor that of the Japanese.” In a rush: I’m the one who poisoned him! I told him those plants were probably safe.”

“If that is the trouble.”

“What else could it be? And they seemed so—so identical in every way with—”

De Barros frowned and chewed his mustache. “Precisely. I admit to thinking you were overcautious, and only followed your example because—Bern, never mind why. Don’t blame yourself. You did your best, short of telling him a falsehood. Besides, it may well be something else. He may have picked up an infection. We have not absolutely proved that no indigenous germ can affect us. Or he may have been exposed to a factor that we were too, but had an idiosyncratic reaction. Without intensive clinical study, there is no telling.”

“Then there’s no treatment” She swallowed hard. He nodded. “Nothing but supportive treatment, and prayer that his body can throw off the effects by itself.”

“We have a whole damn pharmacy along.”

“But what drug to use?” de Barros reminded her. ‘What antibiotic might work on a Cleopatran microbe? Or if this is an allergy, do we want antihistamine, antivenin, or, what? If it is an organ-specific toxin, which does it attack and what is the antidote?” He clenched his fists. “We dare not medicate on a guesswork basis. Most drugs have side effects. We could too easily touch off a synergism, where between them the disease and the ‘cure’ kill him. And while this radio blackout lasts, we can’t even get professional advice.”

“How does he seem to be doing—honestly?” Janne made herself ask. As a venturer onto several different worlds, de Barros had acquired a good deal of practical knowledge.

The Brazilian’s tone bleakened further. “Not well. Pulse, respiration, temperature, nausea, diarrhea, and the resulting dehydration . . . he is sinking.”

“O God, O God.” Jmne almost cast herself upon his shoulder. But instead—she didn’t quite know the reason—she went off to weep alone.

The native came back.

Janne, huddled on a rock, was first aware of it when sand scrunched. Looking up, she saw the neat dinosaurian shape close to her, ax loosely held, mouth smiling wide as if in anticipation.

“Why—why, Cleo,” she stammered, and scrambled to her feet.

The other being stood a minute longer. Receiving no food, she turned and departed. Her stride took her right over the gifts which lay, gaudy and forgotten, on the shore of the sea which had no name.

It struck through Janne: Couldn’t I follow, observe? It may not be entirely wise to go alone. Still, anything’s better than waiting useless for Arch to die.

She hastened to fetch the sniffer. De Barros had barely noticed what went on. Hands caught white-knuckled behind his back, he paced in circles around the tent. His face seemed well-nigh as haggard as that of the unconscious man within.

“I’m going after Cleo,” Janne said.

De Barros surfaced from his broodings. “No, you mustn’t without a partner, and we can’t leave our comrade.”

“One can tend him as well as two for a short while. Fl be careful. There isn’t any danger, really. I can’t get lost in those open woods, with the sun for a guide. If I should be attacked, besides my gun, I have my legs. I can outrun any reptiloid.” In a surge of gallows mirth: “Remember, nature designed me to weigh ten kilos more than I do here.”

“Nevertheless—” De Barros broke off. It was as if suddenly he no longer saw or heard her.

“I won’t be gone long,” said Janne hastily into the silence that she took for consent. She hurried off in pursuit of the native. Once she cast a glance behind. The Brazilian stood motionless, staring out over the ocean.

She wondered briefly what had entered him, but dropped that question in the excitement of the chase. Though Cleo had disappeared, where tracks in sand met vegetable mat, the detector needle pointed straight inland. Movement was swift through that parklike forest. Presently she saw the being’s head bob and sway above a row of fronds.

Cleo glimpsed her in turn and halted. For a dizzy moment Janne thought, Maybe at last she’ll give me a sign. The creature wandered on. Frustration tasted harsh in Janne’s throat. She followed at a discreet distance.

Why do they all but totally ignore us? Maybe they believe that’s how to treat gods or demons. . . . No. They’ve been careful about us, but not frightened. She took food from me. “Why did she spurn our other offerings?

Cleo drifted in no special direction. She dug up and ate a sugarroot She spied a small theroid on a branch overhead and cast her ax. It missed; the animal scuttled off; she retrieved the weapon and continued her stroll.

Where is the male we met? Where are any more whatsoever? . . . Oh!

Cleo stopped dead. Her tail stiffened. Out from a clump of bushes, jerky, jaunty, shining in sunlight, came a young one of her kind. It could be nothing else, a miniature, half a meter tall, carrying its own doll ax. The darling!

Jan= screamed.

Cleo had hissed and hurled. The baby saw. Barely in time, it sprang aside, wheeled, and fled. Cleo bounded after. She grabbed her weapon on the run. Stems bent, branches snapped. Jaws agape, she bounded in chase.

Horror roared around Janne.

Comprehension exploded it. She sank to the ground and shrieked forth laughter like a woman gone crazy.

Caesar, blazing its rapid way across heaven, stood to westward. The ocean flashed gold above sapphire, turquoise, and arabesqued alabaster. Sands shone, forest glowed, snowpeaks lifted in purity. Wings rode upon crystalling, flowing air.

In that hugeness, vehicle and camp seemed flecks which a stray wind had blown in and would soon blow away again forever. Janne’s heart twisted when she saw how de Barros had erected instruments to observe the sun. Poor haunted man, he needs his own place to hide, she thought, and quickstepped toward him.

Yet, spying her, he dropped the screen on which he had been projecting a magnified disc. He ran. His hair tossed gray and wild. He grabbed her to him and kissed her. “Janne, it worked, it worked!” jubilated in her ear. “Already he is conscious, clear in the brain, slim, he has a little strength and—you did it, you, you, you!” He let her go, save for taking her hand. “Come. He would like to see you.”

In the yellow dimness of the tent, she knelt by Fielding’s bedroll and sobbed for joy. He gave her a shaky smile. His voice was still barely audible. “I-fl, honey. Want to cook me a bowl o’ soup in a while? You pick the recipe.”

“You are getting well?” It was a stupid question, but she had just been snatched out of anguish.

“Yeah. 01’ Doc de Barros thinks I’ll be on my feet in three-four days. Now that the poison’s leaving me, I can take cell stimulants and . . .” His mien turned anxious. “Janne, can you and ... and Roberto ... ever forgive me?”

“For what? You were sick, dear Arch.” She brushed lips across his. “What you can do for us is take care of yourself.”

“I obey. I’ve learned. From here on in, I listen to you.” Fielding uttered a chuckle. “Funny. Eden . . . forbidden fruit . . . this time the man tasted, ‘spite o’ the woman. . . .” His words trailed off.

De Barros touched her. “Come,” said the Brazilian. “Let him rest It is a natural sleep.”

Outside, she drew breath after breath until at last she could say levelly: “Then it was the porkplant.”

“Well, yes and no.” de Barros replied. “You gave me the clue.”

“Me? How in the universe?”

“Granted, a chance remark of yours. However, I have an idea that chance favors those who deserve well. When you were running off—do you remember what you said to me about your weight on Cleopatra?”

“Um-ra-m . . . yes, since you mention it . . . but what—” Janne sat down on a dune and hugged her knees. “Tell me.”

He joined her. “It triggered something,” he explained. “Perhaps I would have gotten the thought anyhow, but probably not in time. Arch was failing fast. I was desperate enough to try anything, if only I could find the least clue.

“Well. Cleopatra is smaller than Earth, therefore its gravity field is weaker. But that weakness is not in pro—

portion. If the two planets had the same density, we would weigh less here than we do. And, actually, if they had the same composition, Cleopatra should be somewhat less dense, because of a smaller mnsks compressing itself less at the core. In fact, the mean density is ten percent more than Earth’s. This must be due to a greater proportion of heavy elements, as the spectrum of Caesar also indicates. Doubtless this whole system condensed later than Sol’s, from a nebula which had had time to accumulate more large atoms. For Cleopatra, that means more radioactivity, a hotter interior, hence the outgassing of as much atmosphere as we have around us—” De Barros shook himself. “I babble. You know all this. I too am a little silly from happiness.”

“Go on,” she urged.

“You recalled the fact to me,” he said. “I realim-d that there must be surface regions where heavy elements happen to be especially concentrated. There are on Earth. Plants in such areas may take up the metals and become toxic. For example, locoweed—seleniumcontaminated desert forage—is a menace to livestock. I heard about that from a ,bailiff on our estate.... If this can happen on Earth, how much more often on Cleopatra?”

Janne straightened. “By glory, Arch’s symptoms did look like arsenic poisoning, didn’t they? Now that you’ve pointed it out!”

“I am not sure what element is responsible,” de Barros said. “Perhaps several. A broad-spectrum chelating drug did the—ah, did the trick.”

He paused before continuing: “I have found that the solar storm has passed its maximum. I estimate we can get a call through in about six more days—C-days, that is. Therefore we can give Arch adequate nourishment without starving ourselves too much—” he grinned—“or resorting to organically grown foods.”

“Splendid,” said Janne absently. Her mind had gone elsewhere, “Animals must have an immunity, whether or not a given soil is metal-bearing. The possibility will be a hazard for humans. Not too bad. It simply means people must check a region before they settle in it, and take what precautions are indicated.”

Surprised, de Barros said, “What? Have you resigned yourself ‘to colonization?”

Janne laughed. “Goodness! I’m sorry, Roberto. Your news made me forget I haven’t told you—or Arch. He’ll be so glad. In spite of his ... his ideas about human supremacy . . . or his dislike of ‘glorified snakes’ . . . I can’t believe he was really single-minded about us overrunning a whole other sentient race.”

“Wait a minute.” De Barros seized her arm. “Do you mean the Cleopatrans. are not intelligent?”

She nodded. “I should have deduced it earlier. Besides the youth of this world, its generally primitive biology, there was the toolmakers’ absolute lack of interest in communication, lack of curiosity, lack of community. My guess is, they’re solitary. Individuals stake out territories, sharing the Hint sources. Male and female meet just in mating season. Yes, I should have realized they aren’t thinkers, long before I did. What clinched it was seeing a small one fending for itself. Consciousness demands learning, which demands parental care. The lowest mammals and birds look after their young. Cleo • . The moment she saw this hatch-ling, she wanted to eat it.”

De Barros sat appalled.

“It escaped,” Janne said. “Don’t be shocked. I was at first, till I realized what the significance was. They’re as unconscious, you might say innocent, as fish or praying mantises.”

“But they make tools!” he protested.

“That was what blinded me too,” she replied. “We know we evolved with tools in our hands. Naturally we supposed that whatever other kind of life uses them must be like us, or at least like our near ancestors.”

She sighed. “The truth is,” she continued slowly, as if to herself, “we’re unique, on our planet, only because we’ve destroyed our brothers. In that moment I remembered what I’d read or seen filmed from long ago when they lived: a sea otter pounding an abalone open against a stone he held on his chest: a beaver colony damming a river; a chimpanzee shaping and wetting a straw to catch termites with. . . . At that, we still have termites, and the other ants, and the bees. They still do things which are much more complicated than chipping stones into one particular shape.

“Not that these—what shall we call them? Fabers? Not that they aren’t wonderful, and important, and with many truths to teach us. How I hope the people who come will spare them.”

She rose, walked from him, gazed out across the sea to its clear and burning horizon. “Eden,” she finished. “We are the serpent”

2300 A.D.

A world grew in all directions from the place of landing. People became different from one another, moving away to create different places and life-styles,, filling up the world. Cleopatra changed. Local flora and fauna retreated before the life from Earth. Two great powers gradually emerged to rule the planet, Dardania in the north of the western hemisphere, Pindaria in the east. Together these two nations controlled most of Cleopatra’s land masses; and what they did not control, island chains and remote mountain settlements, they sought to influence, with a view toward future annexation.

Fabers were first modifledin Dardania. In the beginning they became workers and servants; later they served as dancers and musicians, taking part in the developing Dardanian art forms. At the same time both Dardania and Pindaria continued with covert biological research on the faber form, seeking modffications that might have war applications. Much of this work was senseless, carried out to satisfy the individual bent of the researcher, who in many cases held a dubious scientific competence.

The story of Marcus Binh perhaps sums up the human reaction to the conflict of art, society, and misguided science .. .

—Hela Fenn, Psycho-Soc Colonial Survey, 3300 A.D.